this video is and isn't about salt or
sodium but more so about its better half
potassium and the effect of potassium
has protecting you from your head
exploding or in less eye popping
language preventing your brain from
bleeding out we'll be leaning on this
extensive analysis where in the
researchers compiled 33 studies to tease
out the effects of potassium on
cardiovascular disease like stroke so
does potassium actually do anything if
so how and does potassium universally
affect people or does it affect some
more than others well let's find out
briefly potassium is a mineral and an
electrolyte that your body needs to
function and unfortunately the levels of
pottassium intake in the modern diet are
lower than they were in the past so
these researchers pulled together 22
randomized control trials and 11 cohort
studies those are Association studies to
identify the effect low body potassium
and normal pottassium have on
cardiovascular disease now potassium is
specifically linked to cardiovascular
disease in that it maintains body fluid
and electrolyte balance but what in the
world does that actually mean well we
know that elevated blood pressure is
linked to cardiovascular disease and
people with low potassium levels have
heightened risk of increased blood
pressure but why would potassium have
any effect on blood pressure remember
when I said this is and isn't about
sodium it's the very first thing that I
said and this is where it plays a factor
sodium draws a lot of water with it and
when sodium is heavily found in the
blood water remains with it thereby
increasing the volume in a finite space
your arteries if there's a finite space
in your arteries and blood volume is
high that volume pushes against the
walls of the arteries this is high blood
pressure
potassium regulates sodium in that
potassium activates your adrenal glands
and your heart cells release hormones
these hormones bind to your kidneys and
if we zoom into your kidney cells they
dump a large amount of sodium in the
liquid that is going to be excreted from
your body normally your kidney cells
would reabsorb that sodium further down
the kidney structure but because these
hormones bind they reduce the activity
and amount of key sodium reabsorption
Transporters found on the kidney cells
that means that sodium that's already
been dumped for excretion or for urine
is not collected back up it isn't
recycled thereby lowering sodium levels
and if sodium levels drop body fluid and
blood pressure drop as well there's a
ton more involved in that and related
processes like the Direct effects of
potassium on your blood vessels but we
have a lot to get to so we'll leave it
there for the mechanisms if you're
interested I can dedicate a full video
on the mechanisms of potassium now
though let's look at the clinical data
and see if potassium even has an effect
and if it does do some benefit or suffer
more than others here we are these data
indicate what effect increasing
potassium intake has on systolic blood
pressure it's split into four sections
the top is in people with normal blood
pressure the section beneath that is in
people with high blood pressure the
section below that is in a mixture and
the final section at the very bottom is
the overall effect all studies and
participants considered see that zero at
the bottom and the line up from there
that indicates no benefit of potassium
on blood pressure so if we look at the
overall effect the diamond indicating
the results of all the studies
considered indicates an effect of
potassium in reducing blood pressure we
even see that confirmed statistically
that said that doesn't answer if some
people receive more of a benefit than
others though so if we look at the split
groups it looks like those with high
blood pressure do experience a blood
pressure lowering effect however
interestingly studies in people without
high blood pressure indicate no effect H
why might that be well often one can
consideration is the number of studies
included in the
analysis and while I normally wag my
finger at analyses with too few studies
that's usually only a strong case in
studies that indicate High heterogen
difference in the results between
studies but there's no heterogen here so
it seems less likely that it's a matter
of not enough studies another
possibility is that these people already
have normal blood pressure and that fact
alone means that there's no
physiological point in reducing it
further it's already at a healthy level
or a third linked possibility is that
these people have adequate potassium
levels and adding more does nothing
either way the takeaways here is that
pottassium intake reduces blood pressure
and it reduces it by about five points
in people with high blood pressure that
may not seem like much but what if we
turn our attention to more poignant
outcomes like cardiovascular disease
stroke and so on well same rules apply
as for blood pressure surprisingly
cardiovascular disease and coronary
heart disease metrics do not improve
with potassium intake so does that mean
potassium isn't effective then well
funny enough the very argument that I
dismissed on the blood pressure data is
the one to be applied here across the
board there's moderate to high hyrogen
and only three to four studies so my
inclusion would be more appropriately
stated as not enough data to be sure one
way or another and this possibly Bears
out when looking at stroke as more
studies are included and although there
is a moderate amount of hyrogen here we
still detect an effect of pottassium in
addition I'd also add something unique
about stroke is likely not common in the
other two disease States the other two
are likely more more heavily influenced
by the actual plaque buildup which is
certainly still related to blood
pressure but involves more factors as
well however stroke comes in two primary
forms es schic and
hemorrhagic es schic is more in line
with the buildup of plaque blocking the
blood flow into Downstream areas of the
brain potassium might not help as much
there however hemorrhagic is the actual
breaking open of the blood vessels in
the brain and considering high blood
pressure is the leading Force for that
type of stroke it stands to reason that
pottassium would have a more direct
impact of course that's speculation
because we don't actually have the
granularity on that data here however I
biasedly think that's a reasonable
argument anyway the takeaway here is
that we're not sure of the impact
potassium has on other forms of
cardiovascular disease here but it has a
pretty solid impact reducing stroke risk
in fact about a 24% reduced risk
relative to low potassium levels okay
I'd like to also touch on ways to
increase potassium as well as a
particular warning to potassium
consumption before we get to those two
the researchers indicate a potassium
ratio to aim for and how potassium
intake is especially beneficial for
people consuming a particular diet
that's all part of the extended version
of this video included with The
physionic Insider so if you're
interested in more on this topic or a
huge Library including convenient
summaries on your health check it out
it's linked in the description so after
all that what are some sources of
potassium well bananas avocados apricots
prunes spinach pistachios almonds and
well on the meat front surprisingly
salmon uh there's plenty of others with
varying levels but that's a short list
to get anyone started as for a warning
keep in mind that potassium is
indirectly and even directly working
through the kidneys to reduce sodium in
the blood and overc consuming it which
is hard to do by food but still
something to consider can also be
detrimental particularly in people with
kidney disease since it's the kidneys
that regulate it in the body just like
sodium pottassium is excreted as needed
but that can be a problem for people
with that don't have functioning kidneys
or or don't function normally again
though if you're consuming it from food
sources rather than supplements it's
unlikely to be a major concern so the
takeaways here are that pottassium
likely reduces blood pressure modestly
and although we could not confirm the
benefits to other cardiovascular
diseases we could identify pretty
substantial protection against stroke so
if you don't consume much of potassium
in your diet it's an easy fix to improve
your risk and if you're not convinced
this particular video might offer some
convincing arguments on potassium and
sodium or if not then this one thanks
for hanging out
[Music]